Okay, טוב בוקר טוב. tov boker tov. So today's דף daf is
ל"ג עמוד א', lamed gimmel amud aleph, the penultimate דף daf of
the מסכת. masechet. But we pick up at the very bottom of
ל"ב עמוד ב'. lamed bet amud bet. And we're dealing with the
issue that the משנה mishna when it listed the cities that were
בתי ערי חומה batei arei chomah had only listed a handful and
cities that were primarily mentioned in עזרא נחמיה. Ezra Nechemiah. What's the
explanation of that? What about all the cities from the time of
יהושע? Yehoshua? So the גמרא Gemara had two ברייתות braitas in the
name of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael
in the name of רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי, Rabbi Ishmael b'rabi Yose,
one saying that this is just a sample list but of course
it includes the whole list from the time of יהושע. Yehoshua. And
the other say no, this is the entire list or mostly the
entire list because it basically goes from the time of עזרא. Ezra.
So what's the two opinions? The two opinions is whether you go
by the first קדושה kedusha of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael from the
time of יהושע Yehoshua and you say that that dictates קדושה ראשונה
קידשה לשעתה וקידשה לעתיד לבוא, kedusha rishona kidsha l'sha'ata v'kidsha l'atid lavo,
or do we say that that קדושה kedusha disappeared at the time
of the destruction of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and you go
by the second קדושה kedusha at the time of עזרא, Ezra, קדושה
ראשונה לא קידשה לעתיד לבוא kedusha rishona lo kidsha l'atid lavo and
it goes by the קדושה kedusha of the time of עזרא. Ezra.
So besides that being a very important general מחלוקת, machlokes, what's fascinating
here is that it's being translated not in terms of as I
said issues of soil, but more about issues of place. And that
also the status of בתי ערי חומה batei arei chomah is also
related to קדושה kedusha and it even speaks about they were מקדש
mekadesh the ערי חומה. arei chomah. And as I mentioned yesterday that
actually has some significance in the status of מחנה ישראל machaneh Yisrael
and a certain sense of a קדושה kedusha of the מקום makom
similar to like קדושת ירושלים kedushas Yerushalayim and קדושת המקדש kedushas hamikdash
and so on. So that is interesting, very fascinating that that is
part of the concept here. That also is important when you learn
מגילה. Megilla. Why do they connect the issue of מוקף חומה mukaf
chomah to מוקף חומה מימות יהושע בן נון? mukaf chomah mi'yemos Yehoshua
bin Nun? So one explanation of that could be just that חז"ל
Chazal in general like using prefabricated models. Meaning if you're going to
say a הלכה, halacha, you know, it somehow is better if you
can take a model that exists in another place and apply it
even if it's not an exact fit. So you have that sometimes
for example the beginning of גיטין Gittin discusses sending a גט get
from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, from חוץ לארץ, chutz la'aretz, and it
might use the model of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael as it's defined
for תרומות ומעשרות trumos u'maasros even though it's not really relevant for
the גיטין Gittin question, but it's a predefined model. So that might
be sort of one reason why it focuses for מגילה Megilla on
the same issue. But it's also interesting to think about the idea
about using the concept of קדושת ארץ ישראל kedushas Eretz Yisrael as
a sort of
as giving status in terms of the issue for מגילה Megilla as
well because you know part of the whole problem of מגילה Megilla
is that it was a נס, nes, it was a נס בחוץ
לארץ. nes be'chutz la'aretz. And the גמרא Gemara says that the reason
maybe they went to the עיר מוקף חומה ir mukaf chomah from
the time of יהושע Yehoshua was to give כבוד kavod to ארץ
ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So maybe the כבוד kavod is not only to
talking about the time of יהושע Yehoshua but drawing on the model
of the קדושה kedusha of בתי ערי חומה batei arei chomah like
and not you know at a time דווקא davka when your whole
thing is about being in חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz you're focusing on
the sense of the קדושה. kedusha. Of course we should acknowledge that
the whole problem is that you also go by cities in חוץ
לארץ chutz la'aretz that were מוקף חומה מימות יהושע בן נון, mukaf
chomah mi'yemos Yehoshua bin Nun, like שושן. Shushan. So anyway it's fascinating
the way גמרא מגילה Gemara Megilla connects these two. We're not learning
מגילה Megilla now but it's getting close to פורים Purim so I
figured I had to say something about that. Let's pick up now
from the bottom of ל"ב עמוד ב'. lamed bet amud bet. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this, okay
so the גמרא Gemara says last of the narrow lines according to
the approach that all goes from the קדושה kedusha of the time
of יהושע, Yehoshua, והא כתיב v'ha ksiv the verse in דברים Devarim
says אשר ירשו אבותיך וירשתה, asher yarshu avosecha v'yirashta, the land that
your fathers inherited and then when you return from the exile you
will inherit, so it sounds like that the returning of the exile
is a reinheriting of the land, a resanctification of the land. What
do you do if you say it all goes from the time
of יהושע? Yehoshua? So the גמרא Gemara says הכי קאמר hachi ka'amar
this is what it means: כיון דירשו אבותיך kivan d'yarshu avosecha once
your fathers inherited, ירשת את, yarashta at,
you've inherited it. Meaning you don't reinherit it, you are receiving the
bequest of your forefathers, the inheritance of your fathers. It's not a
reinherit, it's a repossession of the old inheritance. Okay so yes it
says you will repossess it but it doesn't mean you will have
to
reinherit. You will repossess the inheritance of your fathers and that is
the question of קדושה ראשונה kedusha rishona or קדושה שנייה. kedusha shniya.
Okay now the גמרא Gemara says like this, ומי מנו שמטין ויובלות?
u'mi manu shmitin v'yovlos? Is it really true? Because according to the
ברייתא braita that says that they resanctified it at the time of
עזרא, Ezra, it says that they resanctified and began again the whole
שמיטה Shmita and יובל Yovel cycle. So the גמרא Gemara says is
that really true that they did שמיטות ויובלות Shmitas v'Yovlos in the
time of the second בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash? השתא Hashta משיגלה שבט
ראובן ושבט גד mishegalah shevet Reuven v'shevet Gad we mentioned this yesterday
when the tribe of ראובן Reuven and גד Gad וחצי שבט מנשה
v'chatzi shevet Menashe and half of the tribe of מנשה Menashe even
the עבר הירדן Ever HaYarden tribes were sent into exile, even before
ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, the other whatever nine tribes or whatever were
sent into exile by סנחריב, Sancherev, just the tribes in the Trans-Jordan
were sent into exile, בטלו יובלות, batlu Yovlos, the יובלות Yovlos were
nullified. Why? Because we... Assume based on another דרשה Derasha *drasha* that
it says actually the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is about to say the
דרשה drasha *drasha* that it's only when כל יושביה עליה aliyah *kol
yoshveha aleha*, all the inhabitants are in the land, the land is
fully possessed by all the tribes, each tribe in its right ancestral
land, only then there is יובל Yovel *Yovel*. As soon as that
stops, so the יובל Yovel *Yovel* stops. So if even in the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash, *Beis HaMikdash* period the יובל Yovel *Yovel* stopped,
so עזרא Ezra, *Ezra*, דכתיב Dechtiv, *de'chsiv* basically when you get to
עזרא Ezra. *Ezra*, how many people came up at the time of
עזרא Ezra *Ezra*? It says כל הקהל כאחד *kol ha'kahal k'echad*, the
entire community that came that was there in the time of עזרא
Ezra, *Ezra* that came up from בבל *Bavel*, ארבע ריבו אלפים *arba
ribo alafim*, it was forty thousand שש מאות וששים *shesh me'os v'shishim*
and 660.
That's it, forty thousand. So if you only set forty thousand in
the original return of the exile, how do you think you're going
to have יובל Yovel *Yovel* if you don't have יובל Yovel *Yovel*
as soon as you even lost the tribes of ראובן Reuven, *Reuven*
and גד Gad, *Gad*? So let's take a look. Now, הני מני
*hani mani* they could account, דתניא De-tanya, *d'tanya* how do we know
that this is how you do יובל Yovel? *Yovel*? As it's taught
in the ברייתא *Baraisa*, משגלו שבט ראובן ושבט גד וחצי שבט מנשה
*mishegalu shevet Reuven v'shevet Gad v'chatzi shevet Menashe*, as soon as the
tribes of ראובן *Reuven*, גד *Gad* and half of the tribe of
מנשה *Menashe*, Trans Jordan, were sent into exile by סנחריב Sancherev *Sancheiv*,
בטלו יובלות *batlu yovlos*, there was no more יובלות *yovlos*, שנאמר *she'ne'emar*
וקראתם דרור בארץ לכל יושביה *u'krasem dror ba'aretz l'chol yoshveha*, you shall
proclaim liberty throughout the land to all its inhabitants thereof, right? So
לכל יושביה *l'chol yoshveha*, all its inhabitants, בזמן שכל יושביה עליה *b'zman
she'kol yoshveha aleha*, only when all the inhabitants are on the land.
Doesn't mean every single Jewish person, but it means when fundamentally the
Jewish people as a people have possessed the land. ולא vlo משגלו
מקצתן *v'lo mishegalu miktzosan*, I'm sorry, ולא בזמן שגלו מקצתן *v'lo b'zman
shegalu miktzosan*,
and not if some of them are in exile. יכול היו עליה
והיו מעורבין שבט בנימין ביהודה ושבט יהודה Yehuda בבנימין *yachol hayu aleha
v'hayu me'uravin shevet Binyamin b'Yehuda v'shevet Yehuda b'Binyamin*, maybe if they were
there but they were not in their right ancestral place, they were
all living mixed together, you didn't have it divided to tribes. The
reason it quotes just יהודה Yehuda, *Yehuda* and בנימין *Binyamin* is obvious
because those were the two tribes that were there in the time
of עזרא Ezra. *Ezra*. So maybe if you had the tribes, and
presumably all twelve tribes, but maybe you had them and they were
just all mixed together, maybe that would be okay, יהא יובל Yovel
לו *yehei yovel lo*, it would apply. תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar, *Talmud
lomar*, the verse says לכל יושביה *l'chol yoshveha*, all of its inhabitants.
Maybe the דרשה drasha, *drasha* is יושביה *yoshveha*, so they're inhabiting the
land like where they deserve, you know in the way it should
be inhabited. בזמן שיושביה כתיקונן *b'zman she'yoshveha k'tikunan*. Not exactly sure what
the דיוק *diyuk* is, but anyway when they are on the land
like they should be, ולא בזמן שהן מעורבין *v'lo b'zman she'hen me'uravin*,
not when they're mixed up. So as soon as you don't have
all twelve tribes, and even if you had them if they weren't
all in their ancestral lands, it would not be נוהג noheig. *noheig*.
So it wasn't נוהג noheig. *noheig* from the, you know, towards the
end of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash? *Beis HaMikdash* period, how could
you say that when they came back at the time of עזרא
*Ezra* they reinstated the יובל Yovel? *Yovel*? How could that happen? אמר
רב פפא Amar Rav Papa, בר יצחק *amar Rav Papa bar Yitzchak*,
מנו יובלות לקדש שמיטה shmita *manu yovlos l'kadesh shemita*. They're right, they
didn't have יובל Yovel, *Yovel*, but they had the יובל Yovel, *Yovel*
cycle. And the reason they had the יובל Yovel. *Yovel* cycle was
in order to have the שמיטה shmita *Shemita*. שמיטה shmita *Shemita* does
not require all twelve tribes. In order to have the שמיטה shmita
*Shemita* you just had to resanctify the land. So you didn't have
יובל Yovel *Yovel* but you had שמיטה shmita, *Shemita*, but there's a
problem. Can you have שמיטה shmita *Shemita* without the יובל Yovel *Yovel*?
Now that is a double question. One is a question of can
you let's say keep שמיטה shmita *Shemita* if you're not sanctifying the
יובל Yovel *Yovel* also together? The other question, as the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* is going to turn to in a minute, is maybe no,
maybe שמיטה shmita *Shemita* you could have without a יובל Yovel *Yovel*,
but the point is that the cycle will be off. Since יובל
Yovel *Yovel* cycle is a forty-year cycle, fifty-year cycle, and if you
don't have the יובל Yovel *Yovel* then you're doing seven-year cycles and
it throws everything off because you're essentially having forty-nine year cycles not
fifty-year cycles. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* here says you need יובל
Yovel *Yovel* to make שמיטה shmita *Shemita*, but it's not exactly clear
why. Do you need it in order to get the year, the
calendar right, so it's fifty-year cycles? Or do you need it in
order just technically I can't have שמיטה Shmita *Shemita* if I'm not
having יובל Yovel *Yovel*? Now one minute, but either way we'll clarify
that in a minute. The point though is is that there could
be an act of sanctifying the יובל Yovel *Yovel* without the practice
of the יובל Yovel. *Yovel*. The way the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is
conceptualizing this is you don't have the practices of the יובל Yovel,
*Yovel* if you don't have all the tribes in their right place.
But if the central בית דין Beit Din *Beis Din*, the same
one that makes ראש חודש *Rosh Chodesh* and the same one that
decides עיבור *ibbur* year, basically the בית bayit דין *Beis Din* that
sets the calendar, if they sanctify it as a יובל Yovel. *Yovel*
year, that's part of their act of setting the calendar. So this
is the יובל Yovel *Yovel* year which we're not practicing יובל Yovel,
*Yovel* because we don't have everybody here in the land, but it's
still is designated as the יובל Yovel *Yovel year. And that's what
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is assuming. It's assuming that in order to
have שמיטה Shmita *Shemita*, or at least in order to have a
fifty-year cycle, they wanted it designated יובל Yovel *Yovel* year, that's what
they did at the time of עזרא *Ezra* and that had halachic
significance. That was a setting of the calendar even if they did
not actually have the practices of the יובל Yovel *Yovel* year.
So this kind of leads us to conclude שמיטה Shmita *Shemita* is
not דאורייתא Deoraita *d'Oraisa* today?
Possibly, but that's not this גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, I'll mention that in
a minute. Okay תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* discusses that based on another גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*.
Which יובל Yovel *Yovel* have still the practices of שמיטה Shmita, *Shemita*
that are common to שמיטה Shmita, *Shemita* and יובל Yovel. *Yovel* or
this would be...
No, so that's a good point but right presumably not, meaning it's
not just as we know that's true that שמיטה Shmita. *Shemita* also
not working the land applies in יובל Yovel. *Yovel* itself. No, the
simple sense is that when you don't have יובל Yovel *Yovel*, when
you don't have כל יושביה עליה *kol yoshveha aleha*, you don't have
any of the practices of יובל Yovel *Yovel*, not just the distinctive
ones.
Otherwise this would be carrying on a tradition, but in a way
that's breaking tradition.
Yeah, so it's not just tradition... And it also affects the counting.
Okay, so let's take a look now at the top of ל"ג
עמוד א'. הניחא לרבנן, hani cha lerabbanan, so why you would need
to do יובל Yovel that works for the rabbis. דאמרי שנת חמישים
אינה מן המנין, deamri shenat chamishim eina min haminyan, that the year
50 does not start, does not start the next seven-year cycle, so
it's 50-year cycles. So having a יובל Yovel year affects the counting,
affects the calendar. אלא לרבי יהודה דאמר שנת חמישים עולה לכאן ולכאן
למה לי? ela lerabbi yehuda deamar shenat chamishim ola lechan ulechan lama
li? According to Rabbi Yehuda that says that the 50th year of
the יובל Yovel, is really the first year of the next cycle,
so designating it as a יובל Yovel year doesn't affect the calendar.
Because anyway, it's seven-year cycles, it's 49-year cycles, right? There's no—there's no
break year in between. So according to him, who needs a יובל
Yovel, year? You're anyway on seven-year cycles. If you're not going to
practice it, so the גמרא Gemara says: וליעבדו לשמיטה מיהא? veliyavdu lishmita
miha? Just שמיטה Shmita is enough? You don't need the יובל? Yovel.
So the גמרא Gemara says: הא בפלוגתא דרבי יהודה. ha beplugta derabbi
yehuda. All right, great. It's not like Rabbi Yehuda. According to Rabbi
Yehuda, who needed יובל Yovel unless you're practicing יובל? Yovel But if
you're not practicing יובל, Yovel? you don't need it, it doesn't affect
the calendar. So here the גמרא Gemara assumes that when they said
before you needed יובל, Yovel, it's not like you needed to designate
the year in order to have שמיטה Shmita years. You could have
שמיטה Shmita years without יובל. Yovel You needed to designate the year
in order to get the cycles right. Okay, and that's only according
to the rabbis. So according to this, based on the other question
before, if we don't have יובל Yovel, nowadays, do we have שמיטה
Shmita nowadays? The גמרא Gemara would seem like the answer is definitely
yes. Right? The only significance of יובל Yovel is to make the
calendar work in terms of 50-year cycles, and that's only according to
the rabbis that have 50-year cycles. But in terms of the practice
of שמיטה, Shmita, the practice of שמיטה Shmita does not require not
only the יובל Yovel to be practiced, doesn't even really require the
יובל Yovel year, it seems like. All it—the only reason to make
a יובל Yovel year is to get your 50-year cycles.
But Rabbi Yehuda says that יובל Yovel would occur during year one
of the next שמיטה Shmita cycle as opposed to having a יובל
Yovel year and then year one.
Yes, absolutely. So in that year, you would actually have, right, really
only five years to work the land until the next שמיטה Shmita
cycle. Okay. So that's what the גמרא Gemara says. You needed it
for the calendar. So the גמרא Gemara says: one minute, it's not
done. So the גמרא Gemara says: וכי לא מנו שמיטין ויובלות? vechi
lo manu shmitin veyovelot? Can you really say they didn't keep שמיטה
Shmita and יובל Yovel, during the end of the בית המקדש, Beis
Hamikdash. first בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash. I mean, we're not to forget
second בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash Now we're focusing back on the end
of the first בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash והא כתיב, veha ketiv, the
פסוק pasuk says:
מקץ שבע שנים. miketz sheva shanim. ירמיה Yirmiyah is—which is really the
end of the first בית המקדש—is Beis Hamikdash. getting up and is
exhorting the people and saying at the end of seven years תשלחו
איש את אחיו העברי אשר ימכר לך, tishalchu ish et achiv haivri
asher yimacher lach, there,
related to our פרשה, parsha, right, first מצוה mitzvah this week's פרשה,
parsha, sending free this Hebrew slave. So he gets up and he
says, "Send free your Hebrew slave at the end of seven years."
ואבינא בה, vaavina bah, and we ask, what do you mean מקץ
שבע שנים, miketz sheva shanim, at the end of seven years? והא
כתיב, veha ketiv, the פסוק pasuk says: ועבדך שש שנים. veavadcha shesh
shanim. He works six years and he gets freed at the beginning
of the seventh. So what does ירמיה Yirmiyah mean at the end
of the seventh? So ואמר רב נחמן בר יצחק שש לנמכר ושבע
לנרצע. veamar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak shesh lenimkar vesheva lenirtza. So no,
six if you're a normal slave that's sold, you get sent free
at the end of six. But there could be a slave that's
sent free at the end of seven. What is sent free at
the end of seven? If the guy got the ear pierced and
he goes beyond six, then he gets sent free at the יובל
Yovel year. What's the earliest that could occur? In year seven. If
it was year six, then it would make the whole thing—anyway. So
therefore, yes, it could be a guy at the end of seven
years in the case of יובל. Yovel So that's how the גמרא
Gemara reads the פסוק. pasuk. Now, reading the פסוק pasuk that way,
the reason it's significant is because it basically says that in the
time of ירמיהו, Yirmiyahu, there was the possibility of יובל, Yovel? because
he was exhorting the people about the יובל. Yovel Well, ירמיהו Yirmiyahu
was after the whole סנחריב Sancheriv and all the exiles of all
those other tribes. So the גמרא Gemara says: ההוא בתוכחה
כתיב. hahu betochecha ketiv. No, that's just giving them מוסר. mussar. It's
not about practical. דקאמר נביא השלחתם? deka amar navi hashallachtem?
What he's telling them is not that you should do it. He's
saying, "Had you ever fulfilled this verse?" He's giving them מוסר mussar
about everything they didn't do in the past, not about what they
need to be doing in the future. Well, that's a sarcastic remark.
Well, it's sarcastic, but it's rhetorical. Sarcastic, right. Okay. Anyway, but it's
the point about what they didn't do in the past. So the
גמרא Gemara says: והא כתיב, veha ketiv, but the פסוק pasuk says—but
you can't say it's just about the past—it says: וישמעו וישלחו. vayishmeu
vayishallachu.
They listened to him and they sent them free. So he is
talking about the present. So the גמרא Gemara says: אלא אמר רב
נחמן. ela amar Rav Nachman. So you know what? You're right. They
did have יובל Yovel. at the end of the בית המקדש Beit
HaMikdash period, the first בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. How is that possible?
What about all the tribes? So it says: ירמיה החזירן ויאשיהו בן
אמון מלך עליהם. Yirmiyah hechiziran veYoshiyahu ben Amon malach aleihem. ירמיה Yirmiyah
went on a special mission and he went into בית אל
Beis El and he collected members of all the 12 tribes. I'm
not sure if the גמרא Gemara imagined how many people he actually
brought back, but he brought back representatives of all the 12 tribes,
or at least some significant section of כל ישראל, Klal Yisrael, and
he brought them back and they dwelt back in their lands, and
יאשיהו Yoshiyahu was the king of all the 12 tribes. Okay, so
it's a pretty sort of fantastical
possibility
that the גמרא Gemara is imagining that he actually brought back not
only those that were from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael proper. proper, but
even ראובן, גד, and חצי שבט מנשה. Chatzi Shevet Menashe. All representatives
of all tribes were brought back by ירמיהו Yirmiyahu and יאשיהו Yoshiyahu
was king of all 12 tribes. רבי, Rebbe, 12?
What? 12 people.
Could be, I mean some ראשונים Rishonim actually say that. You don't
need the majority of the tribes, you need just a little representative.
Okay. ומינלן דהדר, Uminlan dehador,
how do we know that they—that he brought them back? דכתיב, dechtiv,
כי המוכר אל הממכר לא ישוב, Ki hamocher el hamimkar lo yashuv,
because when—again when
יחזקאל Yechezkel here, it's not ירמיה, Yirmiyah, is talking about, you know,
now that we have a חורבן הבית, Churban Habayit, he's saying, oh,
now that there's a חורבן, Churban, there will no longer be a
יובל, Yovel. lands don't go back, ancestral lands don't go back,
this is after the חורבן, Churban, which makes it sound like before
the חורבן Churban ancestral lands did go back. So again, reinforces the
question that it seems like the יובל Yovel, was נוהג. noheig. אפשר
יובל בטל ונביא מתנבא על שיבתו? Efshar Yovel batel unavi mitnabe al
shivato?
What does it mean? Is it possible that the—that the יובל Yovel,
was already—you
know—annulled from way back when in the time of סנחריב and here
יחזקאל Yechezkel is saying, oh, it's no longer going to happen? אלא,
Ela, must be. So again, it's funny, you know, you're turning the
question into the answer. The whole question was oh, it looks like
the יובל Yovel. was נוהג. noheig Ah, it must be that they
returned the 12 tribes. What's my proof they returned the 12 tribes?
Because it looks like the יובל Yovel. was נוהג. Because we see
what יחזקאל Yechezkel is basically saying, that now there won't be a
יובל. Yovel. So you see that there was a יובל. Yovel? אלא
מלמד שהחזירן ירמיהו, Ela melamed shehechziran Yirmiyahu, that ירמיהו Yirmiyahu must have
returned them. ומינלן דיאשיהו מלך עליהם, Uminlan deYoshiyahu malach aleihem, how do
you know יאשיהו Yoshiyahu was the king? דכתיב ויאמר, Dechtiv vayomer,
it says by the פסוק Pasuk by יאשיהו, Yoshiyahu, מה הציון הלז,
Ma hatziyun halaz, what is this tombstone אשר אני רואה asher ani
roeh that I see? So this is when יאשיהו Yoshiyahu was sort
of passing through parts of ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. ויאמרו אליו אנשי
העיר, Vayomru eilav anshei hair, the people of the city said, הקבר
איש האלהים, Hakever ish haElokim, this is the grave of a man
of God אשר בא מיהודה ויקרא את הדברים asher ba miYehuda vayikra
et hadevarim that came from יהודה Yehuda, and he called
these—the—these things האלה אשר עשית, ha’eileh asher asita,
he prophesied about what you—what you just did here, this man of
God had prophesied about it a while ago על המזבח בית אל,
al hamizbeach Beit El, by the altar בית אל. Beit El. Okay,
so fine, we don't have to worry about that whole narrative. The
interesting thing is that he's in בית אל. Beit El. Okay, so
בית אל Beit El is not from יהודה, Yehuda it's from the
rest of ישראל. Yisrael. ומה טיבו של יאשיהו בבית אל? Uma tivo
shel Yoshiyahu beBeit El? What's he doing in בית אל? Beit El?
אלא משהחזירן ירמיהו יאשיהו מלך עליהם. Ela mishehechziran Yirmiyahu Yoshiyahu malach aleihem.
Since he was in בית אל, Beit El, he was outside of
יהודה, Yehuda he was in the land of ישראל, Yisrael, so we
see that he had some business there. So it must be that
the people—there were people there that he was ruling over. Okay, so
to answer the question about it looks like actually the יובל Yovel
was not dependent on all the 12 tribes, the גמרא Gemara imagines
that there was a brief period at the end of the בית
המקדש Beit HaMikdash where there was some representative of all the 12
tribes. רב נחמן בר יצחק אמר מהכא, Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak amar
mehacha, from the following verse, גם יהודה שת קציר לך בשובי שבות
עמי, Gam Yehuda shat katzir lach beshuvi shevut ami,
even יהודה will make a קציר, Katzir, and the דרשה drasha is
קצין Katzin like a ruler over you, over ישראל Yisrael when I
return the—the returning of my people. So again a prophecy that—well actually
it's after the time of—no, הושע Hoshea was right—during that time, excuse
me. Anyway, that there would be a—a ruler,
the way it's being read, a ruler of יהודה over ישראל. Yisrael.
Now, so according to that, anyway, we've somehow solved that problem that—that
we can deal with the fact that it sounds like יובל Yovel
was נוהג in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash, It sounds very clearly
that it was not during the second. I want to remind you
about the problem that תוספות Tosafot raised, which was the fact that
why הלל Hillel had to make a תקנה Takana about throwing the
money in the—in the, you know, in the box in order to
get back your—your house in a בית ערי חומה Beit arei choma
if there was no יובל Yovel in the time of—of הלל Hillel
that would have been practiced. So תוספות Tosafot imagines an answer similar
to this גמרא's Gemara answer. תוספות Tosafot. imagines that yes, in the
time of the second בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash. as well, you know,
maybe they managed to restore some representatives of all the whole 12
tribes, which is about as—you know—hypothetical—about along—the
same lines, you know, about what we would have normally expected. In
terms of—let me read you the line of תוספות. Tosafos. מיהו מכל
שבט ושבט חברו מקצתן. Mihu mikol shevet vashevet chavru miktazan.
Even though there was only 40,000 in the time of עזרא, maybe
there was a small representative of all. Of course, that goes against
this whole גמרא Gemara. because the whole גמרא Gemara before said, right,
emphasized that they did not have יובל Yovel, in the time of
עזרא. So anyway, there's—there's unquestionably, you know, the simple sense not only
of the פסוקים Pesukim but of the גמרא Gemara, right before, it
said, you know, it said that in the time of עזרא they
didn't have יובל, Yovel they might have only designated it for the
sake of creating the cycle. So you don't really know why הלל
Hillel required his תקנה Takana about buying back the walled city—the—the house
in the walled city. Maybe he did it just as a hypothetical.
He was like offended, you know, not offended, but disturbed by the
possibility that this person would be able not to have this and
he had to put it on the books. Of course, it didn't
sound that way. It sounded from the משנה Mishna that people actually
went into hiding and he was addressing a practical issue. So there
is a possibility that the ראשונים Rishonim come up with, which is
maybe there was a דרבנן Derabanan יובל Yovel, during that period. There
wasn't a דאורייתא יובל, Yovel but there was a דרבנן Derabanan יובל.
yovel. So there's one interesting question, which is even though the גמרא
Gemara has solved the problem of the יובל yovel. in the first.
בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash here it makes it sound and the פסוקים
psukim make it sound like there was no יובל yovel? in the
second בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash, How do you deal with הלל's Hillel
תקנה? takanah? That's one question. But the other question is, is there
שמיטה nowadays? Even assuming that, you know, we whether you go by
first קדושה, Kedushah, second קדושה, Kedushah, there is קדושת ארץ ישראל Kedushas
Eretz Yisrael nowadays, is there שמיטה or do we think that שמיטה
is somehow dependent on the יובל? yovel, And that depends on a
גמרא Gemara in גיטין Gittin which speaks about how הלל's Hillel other
תקנה takanah פרוזבול. pruzbul. And the גמרא's Gemara bothered how he can
make a תקנה takanah of פרוזבול pruzbul to do an end run
around even if technically it works around a מצוה מן התורה mitzvah
min haTorah and the גמרא's Gemara. answer seems to be that well,
you know, the nullifying of debts is only rabbinic nowadays so he
had more latitude to do it. It depends exactly how you read
the גמרא. Gemara So anyway, some ראשונים Rishonim read, so there's a
whole question how you read it, maybe you don't even have to
read it that way, but some ראשונים Rishonim read that it means
that everything is rabbinic. When there's not a יובל, yovel then there
is not, not, here the גמרא Gemara said you needed יובל yovel,
to create the calendar, but some say based on that גמרא, Gemara
if you don't have the practice of a יובל, yovel. you don't
actually have the practice of שמיטה, even though it has קדושה, Kedushah,
תרומות ומעשרות, Trumos U'Maasros, whatever, you don't have a biblical practice of
שמיטה, only a rabbinic practice of שמיטה. Others read that גמרא Gemara
other ways. Maybe you don't have the nullifying of debt. If you
think about it conceptually, the nullifying of debt by שמיטה is the
one aspect of שמיטה that is most similar to the יובל yovel
ideas, right, about sort of, you know, reverting things and a forgiving
of debts and all that type of a thing. So maybe that
doesn't apply biblically nowadays, but maybe שמיטה does. So anyway, there's a
whole question about whether שמיטה nowadays is biblical. Is it tied to
the יובל yovel, or not? That's very relevant for the whole issue
of היתר מכירה. heter mechira. Rav Kook's idea that you could sell
the land of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael in order to deal with,
you know, the restrictions of שמיטה, he said really he only wants
to use apply was only prepared to apply assuming that we say
שמיטה is only rabbinic nowadays. So the question about the שמיטה's dependence
on יובל Yovel is a very important question that plays out in
the גמרא Gemara in גיטין. Gittin. The last issue I'll just mention
is that this גמרא Gemara makes it sound very clearly that in
the second בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, they designated a יובל Yovel year
even though they didn't practice יובל Yovel and had fifty-year cycles. Nowadays
the רמב"ם Rambam says we have forty-nine year cycles. We don't designate
a יובל Yovel year and we have forty-nine year cycles. So when
exactly that changed is also an interesting question, okay? So a lot
of issues here about the dependence of שמיטה to יובל, Yovel whether
we have fifty-year cycles, forty-nine year cycles, whether we had יובל Yovel,
in the second בית המקדש, a lot of questions that are not,
you know, fully resolved here. Yes, you had a question, Charlie?
Yeah, regarding the possibility of some members of the ten tribes coming
back during the second בית המקדש, ספר עזרא ונחמיה Sefer Ezra V'Nechemia
has a lot of genealogy in it and they don't mention anything
about the other tribes and it's a surprising omission if that was
the case.
That is a very good point. Okay, anyway, it's a question on
תוספות. Tosafos תוספות Tosafot is really the only one who says it.
Is it just a question of when seven years and when the
שמיטה year is, like does that have to probably have to be
reestablished? Right.
So the רמב"ם, Rambam, there's a famous רמב"ם Rambam in שמיטה ויובל
Shmita V'Yovel where he talks about the importance of a מסורה mesorah
because he basically says, you know, מסורה היא בידינו מימות הגאונים ששמיטה
ידועה בכל ישראל mesorah hi beyadeinu mi'ymos ha'gaonim she'shmita yeduah be'chol Yisrael
and he says what the year is, etc., etc. That being said,
there's a lot of debate in ראשונים Rishonim when exactly the year
was and that's also where the רמב"ם Rambam brings up the issue
about forty-nine year cycles as opposed to fifty-year cycles. But yeah, we
we really just rely on מסורה mesorah for that then, but there
if you look at the ראשונים Rishonim around there, there's there is
debate. So have they tried to calculate it or? No, because, well,
yeah, the question
I assume people have tried to calculate it. Part of the question
also, like I said, has to do with if there was a
shift from fifty-year cycle to forty-nine year cycle, you have to know
when that shift occurred or you can't calculate
and then there's all kinds of other calendrical problems that we
had we had a whole session on. Yes. So for possibility of
reestablishing יובל Yovel. today, we if we need all twelve tribes, there's
no one alive in the world who identifies as being part of
בני אשר, Bnei Asher, for instance. Right. This is a problem. So
okay, so we'll wait until
אליהו הנביא Eliyahu HaNavi comes. Okay, moving on. בתי החצרים. Batei HaChatzeirim.
Now all of that was about houses in walled cities. What about
houses in unwalled cities? So obviously you don't have the right to
force it the guy to resell it back to you at the
end of a year, right, you don't have the power of houses
in walled. Do you get it back at the יובל? Yovel. Do
you have a right to buy it back after the year? Is
it like a field, right? What's the story about a field? You
can buy it back after two years. So what is the status
of houses in unwalled cities? בתי החצרים, Batei HaChatzeirim, houses in unwalled
cities, נותנים להם כל היפה שבבתי ערי חומה וכל היפה שבשדות. nosnim
lahem kol ha'yafeh she'be'batei arei chomah ve'kol ha'yafeh she'ba'sados.
So actually, as opposed to what I said because, you know, because
that that
that you would think you do not have the power to buy
it back within the year, the משנה Mishnah here says actually you
don't have the limitations of the בתי ערי חומה batei arei chomah
but you have the power of the בתי ערי חומה batei arei
chomah that you can actually you can force to buy back within
the year and you have the power the privileges of the field
you can force to buy back after two years. So actually the
only time you cannot force to buy back is during the second
year. for the seller. So you can force to buy back in
the first year, you can force to buy back from the second
year on. נגאלים מיד, Nigalim miyad, it is redeemed right away, that's
like the בתי חצרים. Batei Chatzerim. בכל שתים עשר חודש, B'chol shtaim
asar chodesh, and for the entire twelve months כבתים, K'vatim, like the
houses. Okay, and ויוצאים ביובל ובגירעון כסף כשדות. V'yotzim bayovel u'v'giron kesef
k'sadot.
Not only that, but that in the remainder it will return to
you in the יובל Yovel, like a field, and not only will
it return and you can redeem it for the rest of the
time. Now here's another point. When you redeem a field during the
rest of the time, when you redeem a house, if you remember,
during the first year you pay the full purchase price. When you
redeem a field during the rest of the time, you don't pay
the purchase price, what you do is you do the proportional based
on the years left. So that's the phrase here of ובגירעון כסף.
U'v'giron kesef. So during the first year you can buy it back
at the full price like a house. During the rest of the
years, not the second year, that falls between the two, but presumably
from year three on, you can buy it back based on the
proportion, not the fixed price, because the fixed price was only for
fields, but the proportion of the purchase price as if it were
a field. So you use the idea of proportion but you don't
use the fixed price set for fields. Okay, and you'll get it
back in the יובל. Yovel. So again, it's not clear. The פסוקים,
psukim, the פסוקים psukim you might have thought you have, you know,
none of the power, you wouldn't have thought anyway, you none of
the power maybe, none of the privileges, here it assumes that you
just don't have the limitations. All of the privileges and the rights
of all things you have in these, in these fields, which is
pretty amazing.
על גאולתו תהיה לו וביובל יצא. Al geulato tihyeh lo u'vayovel yetzei.
But
is it clear that you could do that? Force it, meaning in
the פסוקים psukim I think you would have assumed that it would
have been like the שדות, sadot, right? In the פסוקים psukim would
you have assumed you could have forced the sale back during the
first year? על גאולתו
תהיה לו וביובל יצא.
Al geulato tihyeh lo u'vayovel yetzei.
I don't know, I think the פשט, pshat, I mean you're right
obviously that's how חז"ל Chazal are reading it, but I would have
thought the פשט pshat more would have said that it's like a,
meaning we have two models. We have the שדה sadeh clearly, the
שדה sadeh and the בתי ערי חומה. batei arei chomah. I would
have thought that it says בתי חצרים, batei chatzerim, it's like a
field. It's like you can redeem it, you know, for a long
period of time, you're not limited to a year and it goes
out in the יובל. Yovel. Anyway, so that's what I would have
assumed, but the משנה Mishnah here assumes that no, you still retain
the privileges of the בתי ערי חומה. batei arei chomah. You don't
have the limitations, you still have the privileges and you can buy
it back during the first year. Let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, we taught. על שדי הארץ יחשב,
Al sedei ha'aretz yeichashev, right?
Because that's what it says, right? על שדי הארץ יחשב, Al sedei
ha'aretz yeichashev, it's field of the land. So the simple sense of
the פסוקים psukim would have been just treat it like a שדה.
sadeh. Okay, not as nothing like a house. הקישו הכתוב לשדה אחוזה.
Hikisho hakatuv l'sadeh achuzah. מה שדה אחוזה יוצא ביובל, Mah sadeh achuzah
yotzei bayovel, as as שדה אחוזה וביובל יצא, sadeh achuzah u'vayovel yetzei,
it will go back in the יובל, ובגירעון כסף, u'v'giron kesef,
and you can buy it back proportional to the amount to the
price during those remainder years. גאולה תהיה לו. Geulah tihyeh lo. אף
בתי חצרים יוצאים ביובל ובגירעון כסף. Af batei chatzerim yotzim bayovel u'v'giron
kesef. Fine. So that's I think what I would have said פשט
הפסוקים. pshat hapsukim. It's like a field. But the משנה Mishnah goes
further and says you also have the privileges of a or the
rights of a בית that you can force the sale back in
the first year. ואי מה שדה אחוזה אינה נגאלת פחות משתי שנים,
V'ee mah sadeh achuzah einah nigelet pachot mishtei shanim,
maybe I should say it's fully like a field that it can't
be redeemed within two years. אף בתי חצרים אינם נגאלים פחות משתי
שנים, Af batei chatzerim einam nigalim pachot mishtei shanim, maybe here you
can't redeem it within two years. תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, גאולה תהיה
לו, Geulah tihyeh lo, which is how דב Dov was reading the
פסוק pasuk through the how the משנה Mishnah is reading the פסוק.
pasuk. No, the the emphasis of גאולה תהיה לו Geulah tihyeh lo
is to tell you as all rights of redemption. מיד, Miyad, you
can redeem it right away just like a house. הואיל ונתת להם
כח יפה שבשדות וכח יפה שבבתים. Ho'il v'natata lahem koach yafeh shebashadot
v'koach yafeh shebavatim. Now that you've given them all of the rights
of fields and all of the rights, meaning for the seller, not
for the buyer, of the houses, יכול לא יצאו ביובל? Yachol lo
yetzu bayovel? Maybe they shouldn't go out by the יובל, which is
pretty funny, we just said it does, and the פסוק pasuk says
it does, וביובל יצא. u'vayovel yetzei. But maybe, hey, you're giving this
guy so much, maybe he shouldn't have a right to get it
back in the יובל. תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar, וביובל יצא. u'vayovel yetzei.
הא, Ha, the פסוק pasuk says explicitly it goes back in the
יובל. So the
גמרא Gemara says
מאי קאמר, mai ka'amar, what type of הוה אמינא hava amina was
that? We already said it's like a field, so of course it
goes back in the יובל. What what do you mean, maybe it
doesn't go back in the יובל? אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna,
לא נצרכה אלא במקדיש בית בבתי חצרים. lo nitzrecha ela b'makdish bayit
b'vatei chatzerim.
Ah, here's the point. Let's say we're not talking about a sale.
We're talking about sanctifying. I have my house in the unwalled city,
וגאלו אחר מיד הקדש. u'gealo acher miyad hekdesh. And again, like we've
been talking before, when I I think of my field, now I
think of my house. דוד David comes and he buys it off
of הקדש. hekdesh. Now if that was a field, what would happen?
יובל would come, what would happen to the field? It would go
to, anybody remember? כהנים. kohanim. Now since we are treating this like
a field, maybe when I sanctify my house and you redeem it,
maybe also goes to the כהנים. kohanim. Okay, ופגע בו יובל, u'paga
bo yovel, now the יובל hits it, בשנה שניה, bashanah shniyah, in
the second year. Now, למאי מדמית ליה, L'mai medamit leh, what are
you going to compare it to? We'll talk about why the second
year in a minute. אי לבתי ערי חומה מדמית לה, ei l'batei
arei chomah medamila, so after the first year had passed, meaning, if
we were to give me the rights of we treat this as
a בית לבתי ערי חומה. bayis l'batei arei chomah. What happens? Remember
what happens when I sanctify my house in בתי ערי חומה batei
arei chomah and David buys it? He has a year from הקדש,
hekdesh, he has a year from the time he purchased it from
הקדש, hekdesh, right? That and if I don't buy it back from
him during that year, he gets it permanently. So that's what happened,
I sanctified this house, but it was in an open city, and
David redeemed it. If and now a year after he redeemed it
has passed. How am I going to treat it? If I treat
it like בתי ערי חומה, batei arei chomah, he gets it completely,
right? Because that's what it would be like בתי ערי חומה. batei
arei chomah. חליט ליה לוקח. chalit lei lokeach. אי לשדה אחוזה מדמית
לה, ei l'sdei achuzah medamila, if it's like a if it was
like a field, so what happens when the יובל hits? It goes
לכהנים l'Kohanim נפקא. nafka. It goes to the כהנים. Kohanim.
That's why we said second year, meaning, if it's after the first
year I've lost the ability to get it back from you like
a house, and because of the יובל, if it's a field it
goes to the כהנים, Kohanim, so maybe I don't get it at
that stage. We don't know of course what happens, does David get
it or the כהנים Kohanim get it, but at least I wouldn't
get it at that stage, right? So therefore, הכי איצטריך וביובל יצא.
hachi itztareich u'vayovel yeitzei.
That's why it says וביובל יצא, u'vayovel yeitzei, to tell me I
have a privilege that transcends those two categories. That even when I
sanctify it and you buy it, and even though according to either
category I wouldn't get it back, now, when יובל hits I get
it back regardless. Okay. וביובל יצא. u'vayovel yeitzei. So מתקיף לה רבי
זירא, matkif lei Rebbi Zeira, מאי איריא גאלו אחר, mai irya ge'alo
acher, אפילו לא גאלו נמי. afilu lo ge'alo nami.
Why do you have to give the example that David redeemed it?
Just give the example that it's sitting in הקדש's hekdesh property. Now
David redeemed is a better example because that's a case where he
would have gotten permanently otherwise anyway.
But why did you have to describe it that way? The same
would be true if it was sitting in הקדש, hekdesh, I would
get it back at the יובל, which would not necessarily be the
case by the case of the field or whatever. אמר ליה
אביי, amar lei Abaye, שלא יאמרו הקדש יוצא בלא פדיון. shelo yomru
hekdesh yeitzei b'lo pidyon. No, because if it were sitting in הקדש
hekdesh and we're going to see that this is going to be
a problem at the end of this דף, daf, then it would
go straight back to me. Remember we have the problem when I
sanctified my field and nobody redeemed it and it went to the
כהנים, Kohanim, maybe before the כהנים Kohanim possess it, they have to
pay for it because something has to transfer the קדושה kedusha off.
So in that scenario, it would not have just directly gone back
to me, maybe I would have had to pay some money in
order to transfer the קדושה. kedusha. So we gave the scenario that
David bought it, so that it's no longer sanctified and then it
goes back to me. But basically what we're saying now is that
this has all of the privileges of a walled city, all the
privileges of a field for the seller, and not only that, even
a privilege that transcends it. When it's sanctified and redeemed, even though
in all those categories I wouldn't get it back, in this case
I do get it back. So again, one can speculate, פשוטו של
פסוקים pshuto shel pesukim is that it's just like a field and
then it's not a big deal. There're two categories, there's houses which
walled cities have a special status which we discussed why the other
day, and everything else which has a הלכה halacha of going back
in the יובל and has the same הלכה. halacha. According to this
you have to really ask, why is the תורה Torah giving me
so many rights in this, more than it gives me in everything
else? And I imagine that the answer is that look, I've got
to live somewhere. You know it's kind of like it's kind of
like the תורה's Torah you know sort of like a housing initiative.
So on the one hand, a house in a walled city, you
know not everybody has to live in a metropolis, not everybody you
know that's expensive real estate, you you you know you don't necessarily
maybe more transitory anyway, so you don't necessarily have the same entitlement
there, okay? And therefore, it's not a problem, it goes to other
people, it's more like commercial land and so on. But houses outside
in the villages, not in the metropolis, those are the houses that
are connected to my farms and my lands and which is the
whole idea of the ancestral idea which is what the תורה Torah
is so מקפיד makpid on. So that explains why it says as
good as the field and maybe it's even better, because I can
sell my field and still live somewhere, but here, you know, I've
got but I can't sell my house, where am I going to
live? So I think that's a way of understanding how the גמרא
Gemara approaches this, that it gives me all of those privileges even
more than everything else. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. מנלן, menalan, how do I know that הקדש hekdesh will not
go without being redeemed? מבין לוי. miben Levi. מה בן לוי שיפה
כוחו בממכרו הורע כוחו בהקדשו. mah ben Levi sheyafeh kocho b'memkaro hura
kocho b'hekdesho. A לוי Levi has greater power when he sells. What
does he have greater power when he sells? Because if you remember
when a לוי Levi sells his you know it says גאולת עולם
תהיה ללוים. ge'ulat olam tihyeh l'Levi'im. When they sell their land they
are always entitled to redeem it, you know, they're not limited to
the one year or whatever, they can always redeem it. Nevertheless,
הורע כוחו בהקדשו. hura kocho b'hekdesho. When he
actually sanctifies it
and he gets it back, he has to give some money. The
same idea that הקדש hekdesh is not יוצא בלא פדיון. yeitzei b'lo
pidyon. You don't want to remove the הקדש hekdesh without there being
some money that it transfers. So even a לוי Levi that has
all this power when it comes to transactions with selling his field
or houses, when it comes to הקדש... hekdesh... he has to actually
give money, ישראל שהוא כוחו בממכרו, Yisrael shehu kocho bemimkaro, an ordinary
ישראל Yisrael that normally does not have all the powers, by the
house of the unwalled city, he's got a lot of powers. But
in general, he has limits to his rights when it comes to
normal transactions. So it's כל שכן שרע כוחו בהקדש. kol sheken shera
kocho be-hekdesh. How much more so that when he sanctifies, even if
it's the house in an unwalled city that he has all these
rights to, how much there still has to be when it comes
to הקדש hekdesh some transfer of the קדושה, kedusha, some פדיון. pidyon.
והתם מנלן, Ve-hatam minalan, how do we know this is true by
לוי? Levi? דתניא, ויצא ממכר בית. ve-yatza mimkar bayis. שומע אני אף
עבדים ומטלטלין ושטרות. shomeia ani af avadim u-metaletlin u-shetaros. Maybe
even, hold on a second...
right, so what's the פסוק? pasuk? The פסוק pasuk says, ואשר יגאל
מן הלוים ויצא ממכר בית ועיר אחוזתו ביובל. ve-asher yiga'al min ha-Leviyim
ve-yatza mimkar bayis ve-ir achuzato ba-yovel. Let me just read the פסוק
pasuk exactly. I have it right here. You have it? So go
ahead, read it for us. Okay, where is it?
Top of the page, there.
Thank you. וערי הלוים בתי ערי אחוזתם גאולת עולם
תהיה ללוים. Ve-arei ha-Leviyim batei arei achuzatam geulat olam tiheyeh la-Leviyim. Right,
so they can always redeem anything they've sold. ואשר יגאל מן הלוים
ויצא ממכר בית ועיר אחוזתו ביובל. Ve-asher yiga'al min ha-Leviyim ve-yatza mimkar
bayis ve-ir achuzato ba-yovel. Somebody buys it, right, or buys it maybe
off of הקדש, hekdesh, we'll see, then it returns to them in
the יובל. כי בתי ערי הלוים היא אחוזתם בתוך בני ישראל. Ki
batei arei ha-Leviyim hi achuzatam betoch benei Yisrael. Okay, so they're going
to get it back. So now let's take a look at how
we're using that. ויצא ממכר בית. Ve-yatza mimkar bayis. שומע אני אפילו
עבדים ומטלטלין ושטרות. Shomeia ani afilu avadim u-metaletlin u-shetaros. Maybe even if
it's not his plot of land, maybe he gets back everything. Maybe
even if I buy his his slaves or his car, maybe he
gets it back in the יובל. תלמוד לומר בית. Talmud lomar bayis.
No, house. ועיר אחוזתו מה תלמוד לומר? Ve-ir achuzato mah talmud lomar?
ועיר אחוזתו. Ve-ir achuzato. So then מה תלמוד לומר ממכר? mah talmud
lomar mimkar? If it's only talking about houses and fields, those are
the only things that goes back, why does it say "the things
that he sold," which seems to be a much bigger category, like
anything he sells he gets back? ממכרו יוצא בחינם ואין הקדש יוצא
בחינם. Mimkaro yotzei be-chinam ve-ein hekdesh yotzei be-chinam. Because the emphasis is:
what does he get back in the יובל? Things that he sold
to another person. But things that he sanctified, although he gets them
back in the יובל, they don't go back automatically. He has to
do some פדיון. pidyon. He has to give some money to transfer
the קדושה. kedusha. אלא בפדיון. Ela be-pidyon. Only with a פדיון. pidyon.
Okay, so therefore, and it says, by the way, it's a little
funny because when אביי Abaye said it, שלא יאמרו, shelo yomeru, it
sounded like it was a מראית עין. marit ayin. It sounded like
fundamentally he gets it back, but it doesn't look like... it looks
like the קדושה kedusha disappeared, which it did, and people will wonder,
so do something so it transfers the קדושה. kedusha. But based on
the פסוק, pasuk, it's the same דרשה drasha, context we had before,
right? If I sanctify a field and it goes to the כהנים
kohanim from הקדש, hekdesh, do they have to pay money? Does the
קדושה kedusha transfer, go away automatically? It doesn't need to transfer. Anyway,
here we're pointing to the פסוק pasuk that says even when it
goes from הקדש hekdesh back to the לויים, Leviyim, something they sanctified,
it's only when they redeem it first. And the same would be
true about your house in an unwalled city. You might get it
back, but if you're getting it back straight from הקדש, hekdesh, there
needs to be some money to transfer the קדושה kedusha to. Yes.
It sounds like he could redeem it at any time.
Yeah, a לוי Levi can. Yes. Yes, that's the whole point. That's
what the גמרא Gemara said, יפה כוחו. yafe kocho.
So the יובל is irrelevant to them?
Right. Well, it's not irrelevant. They get it back in the יובל,
but they don't have the limit of only during the first year,
only after the second year, whatever they sell of a house and
field, in terms of property, they can redeem immediately and they can
redeem all the way up until the יובל. Okay? So they can
redeem anything, any property they've sold, any landed property a לוי Levi
has sold, that's what the משנה Mishnah is about, גואלים לעולם. goalin
le-olam. They can start redeeming it right away as if it was
a בתי ערי חומה, batei arei chomah, and they can redeem it
all the way until the יובל like it was a field. So
they have similar to almost the power we're giving now in the
case of a house in an unwalled city, the לויים Leviyim have
for all their property. They can... they have no limit. And in
the יובל, of course, they get it back.
They're forced to redeem it.
They're not forced to... if it's in the hands of הקדש hekdesh
and they sanctified it, then they have to give money. But in
any other case, they get it automatically back. So basically, the story
of the לויים Leviyim in all their property is pretty close to
what we're saying right now about somebody in the house in an
unwalled city, with the one possible exception of year two, because year
two might be between the two categories for that case. All right,
so let's keep on going. The גמרא Gemara says like this. ופליג
דרבי יאשיה. U-pelig de-Rabbi Yoshiyah. This argues on רבי יאשיה. Rabbi Yoshiyah.
דאמר רבי יאשיה כולם היו בכלל ונתן הכסף וקם לו. De-amar Rabbi
Yoshiyah kulam hayu bi-chlal ve-nasan ha-kesef ve-kam lo.
All things were in the category of you give the money and
then you get it, which basically means that the way you get
הקדש hekdesh is you have to redeem הקדש. hekdesh. There's actually a
little bit of a problem that this פסוק pasuk doesn't exist. But
anyway, there's a תוספות Tosafot that discusses that. The גמרא Gemara when
it wants to distill the idea that you have to redeem הקדש
hekdesh says ונתן הכסף וקם לו, ve-nasan ha-kesef ve-kam lo, but תוספות
there says it's a hybrid of different פסוקים. pesukim. But we won't
worry about that right now. Anyway, everything followed the rule that you
don't get at הקדש, hekdesh, the קדושה kedusha doesn't remove unless you
redeem it. דכי פירש הכתוב בשדה אחוזה, De-ki peireish ha-kasuv be-sedeh achuzah,
when it says by the field of inheritance, והיתה השדה בצאתו ביובל
קודש לה' כשדה החרם, ve-hayetah ha-sadeh be-tzeitah ba-yovel kodesh la-Hashem ke-sedeh ha-cherem,
that the field when it goes, you know, David redeemed the field
that I sold and it goes to the כהנים. kohanim. שדה הוא
דפרקיה ונפקא לכהנים. Sadeh hu de-prakiah ve-nafka le-kohanim. It's the field because
he redeemed it from הקדש, hekdesh, then it goes to the כהנים.
kohanim. אבל הנך כדקאי קאי. Aval hanach kedakai kaimi. And
but the others are like they were. What does that mean? אבל
הנך, Aval hanach, let me just check רש"י. Rashi. Hold on.
Ah,
okay,
okay.
So meaning, right, right, it's not about black or white, meaning, so
normally, so, so it is only the something, ah, right, right. So
it's only something that David redeemed that was actually redeemed from הקדש,
Hekdesh, the Torah tells you that that goes to the כהנים. Kohanim.
But something that was still in the possession of הקדש, Hekdesh, what's
the normal rule about something in the possession of הקדש? Hekdesh? Something
in the possession of הקדש Hekdesh stays in the possession of הקדש
Hekdesh until somebody redeems it. Okay, so that's what Rabbi Yehoshua is
saying. Rabbi Yehoshua is saying the general rule is something that's הקדש
Hekdesh stays הקדש Hekdesh until it's redeemed. The only time the Torah
says something different, which isn't really different because it was redeemed, is
when as I identified, somebody redeemed it, then it goes to the
כהנים. Kohanim. But if it's sitting in the possession of הקדש Hekdesh
and nobody has redeemed it, then you know what happens when the
יובל hits? Nothing. It remains in the possession of הקדש Hekdesh until
it gets redeemed. So the things that we're discussing about the city
of לויים Levi'im goes back to לויים, Levi'im, or that the house
in the unwalled city goes back to me, that's not like Rabbi
Yehoshua. Rabbi Yehoshua says if it's in the possession of הקדש Hekdesh
when יובל hits it stays. If you remember, there was a similar
position, I think it was Rabbi Eliezer, that said that if I
sanctified a field and it was sitting in the possession of הקדש,
Hekdesh, what happens when יובל rolls around? Many opinions said the כהנים
Kohanim have it, and there's one opinion said no, if it's still
sitting in the possession of הקדש, Hekdesh, it remains in the possession
of הקדש. Hekdesh. Nothing happens while it's in the possession of הקדש.
Hekdesh. Okay, so that's what Rabbi Yehoshua is saying. Okay, now we
go on. שדה הוא דפרקיה אבל הנך כדקאי קאי. Sadeh hu deparkei
aval hanach kedakai kaimi. ובניובל יצא למה לי? u-vanyovel yetzei lamah li?
So then what does he do with ובניובל יצא, u-vanyovel yetzei, since
we were learning it before to say that you get it from
הקדש? Hekdesh? So here we're saying you don't get it from הקדש.
Hekdesh. So אמר רב פפא, לא נצרכה אלא למוכר בית בבתי חצירים.
lo nitzrecha ela lemocheir bayis be-vatei chatzeirim.
I sold my house in this unwalled of the unwalled cities, ופגע
בו יובל בשנה שניה. u-faga bo Yovel be-shanah sheniyah. And now it's
the second year. Okay. And so, what this is again a case
of what falls between the gaps? I sold my house to David,
and now the יובל hits in the second year. If it were,
let's take a look. למאי מדמית ליה? Lema'i medamit lei? Which category
are you going to put it into? אי לבתי ערי חומה מדמית
ליה, Ei le-vatei arei chomah medamit lei, if it's like a house
in a walled city, אפדייה לוקח, afdaye lokeiach,
then after the first year, David should get it, even now it's
the יובל in the second. אי לשדה אחוזה מדמית ליה, Ei lisdeh
achuzah medamit lei, if it's like a field, okay, so I get
back a field that I sold to David, but remember what the
הלכה halakha is? He's entitled to two years. So if he buys
it within one year of the יובל, he gets the year after
the יובל. השלמה בעי. Hashlamah ba'ei. You have to make up the
year after. להכי איצטריך ובניובל יצא. Lehachi itztarich u-vanyovel yetzei.
Therefore, it says ובניובל יצא u-vanyovel yetzei to say you have a
power that transcends those two. תניא כוותיה דרב הונא ותיובתא דרבי יהושע.
Tanya kevasei de-Rav Huna u-tiyuvta de-Rabbi Yehoshua. We taught like Rav Huna,
a contradiction of Rabbi Yehoshua. המקדיש בית בבתי חצירים, Hamakdish bayis be-vatei
chatzeirim, if you sanctify your field, הרי זה גואל מיד, harei zeh
go'el miyad, you can redeem it immediately, וגואל לעולם, ve-go'el le'olam, and
you can always redeem it up to יובל. נגאלו אחר מיד הקדש.
Niga'alo acher miyad Hekdesh. So what happens if somebody else redeemed it?
הגיע יובל ולא נגאל, Higia Yovel velo niga'al, or not only that,
let's say it was never redeemed and sitting in the possession of
הקדש? Hekdesh? חוזר לבעלים ביובל. Chozer labe'alim bayovel. It goes back. So
opposed to Rabbi Yehoshua, as it says if it's sitting in הקדש
Hekdesh it stays in הקדש, Hekdesh, he says it goes back. So
what do we have now? You have that these בתי חצירים batei
chatzeirim have all the powers of these two categories, and in a
way they have something that even goes beyond those. So I can
buy it back right away like the בתי ערי חומה batei arei
chomah at the full price. I can buy it back after a
year or two at the proportional price. And those are those categories.
And I get it in the יובל, so that's like the שדה.
sadeh. And there's ways in which it transcends the יובל. Number one
is if it was sanctified and David bought it or whatever, according
to one opinion, in that case, I'm going to get it back,
even though if it were in those other two categories, it wouldn't
go to me, it would go to the כהנים Kohanim or David
would keep it. Or if it was I sold it to him,
it was a second year, I get it back and he doesn't
get to make up his year afterwards. So there's ways in which
it transcends. The one question the גמרא Gemara does not address is,
once we're saying now that it transcends those two categories, does it,
you know, I would basically still try to fit it into those
two boxes, or we're saying it's pretty much all the rules? Because
then the question would be, how do you deal with the second
year? Can I force David to sell it back to me during
the second year? That's not like a house, it's not like a
field. If I was a לוי, Levi, I could. That's גאולת עולם.
ge'ulas olam. But in this case, that's not spelled out in the
משנה. mishna. Okay, let's take a look now as we wrap up
houses in the unwalled cities, ואלו בתי חצירים. Ve'elu batei chatzeirim. Here's
what defines an unwalled city. Of course, one is that it doesn't
have a wall. But the חידוש chiddush is even if it has
a wall, it might not count. If it's all the things that
didn't count when we were talking about walled cities. So first of
all, שני חצירות של שני בתים. Shnei chatzeiros shel shnei batim. If
you have two streets and they only have and have two houses
each. Remember when we talked about the walled cities, we said you
needed three streets with two houses each. So if you have even
if it's walled, if it's not big enough to be considered a
city, then it's not considered a walled city. It's a walled, I
don't know, house, a hamlet, whatever. Anyway, so if it's only two
streets with two houses, it's not a walled city, אף על פי
שמוקפת חומה מימות יהושע בן נון, af al pi shemukeifas chomah miyamos
Yehoshua bin Nun, even with a wall from the time of יהושע
בן נון, Yehoshua bin Nun, הרי הן כבתי חצרים. harei hen ke-vatei
chatzeirim. It's just as good as an unwalled city. So clearly it
goes without saying if it didn't have a wall. תנו רבנן, Tanu
rabanan, we taught מבית שנאמר בתי החצרים, mibayis shene'emar batei ha'chatzerim, houses
of the unwalled cities. איני יודע שאין להם חומה? eini yodeia she'ein
lahem chomah? Of course it means it doesn't have a
wall. It says
unwalled. מה תלמוד לומר אשר
אין להם חומה סביב, mah talmud lomar asher ein lahem chomah saviv,
that doesn't have a wall around? אף על פי שיש להם
חומה כמי שאין להם חומה. af al pi she'yesh lahem chomah k'mi
she'ein lahem chomah.
There could be cases that it does have a wall and it's
still as if it doesn't have a wall. What would be that
case? It would be the case if it's not big enough. וכמה
בתים וחצרות שנים, ve'chamah batim ve'chatzerot shenayim, how big, what would be
the minimum, you know, size? So here's the דרשה, derashah בתים שנים
חצרות שנים. batim shenayim chatzerot shenayim.
So the דרשה derashah is בתי החצרים batei ha'chatzerim or חצרות. chatzerot.
So two houses, two חצר, chatzer, חצר chatzer not now describing the
whole city as a village but means courtyards or streets. So two
houses, two streets, even with a wall, that doesn't count as a
wall. That's not big enough. Okay. So אף על פי שיש להם
חומה כמי שאין להם חומה וכמה בתים וחצרות שנים, af al pi
she'yesh lahem chomah k'mi she'ein lahem chomah ve'chamah batim ve'chatzerot shenayim, שתי
חצרות של שני בתים, shtei chatzerot shel shnei batim, even
if you have two streets and two houses, then even with the
wall, it's not like it's a walled city. It's not big enough.
ואימא בית וחצר, ve'eima bayis ve'chatzer,
maybe even if you're reading the plural, maybe it's one street and
one house, one street and one house, you have a total of
two streets and two houses. How do you read it to mean
two houses per street? And even that is not yet big enough.
אי הכי לכתוב רחמנא חצרים, in kein lichtov rachmana chatzerim, then why
didn't it say חצרים, chatzerim, why does it say חצרות? chatzerot? I
don't exactly get the דרשה, derashah, but okay. Anyway, so the גמרא
Gemara says like this,
let me just see if רש"י Rashi if I'm missing something in
רש"י. Rashi.
It's the same ending. אי הכי לכתוב חצרות ולא בתי. in kein
lichtov chatzerot velo batei. Oh, no, רש"י Rashi says don't just say
בתי, batei, I'm sorry. It would have just said חצרים, chatzerim, a
חצר chatzer means a street with a house. So since it adds
the words בתים, batim, the גמרא Gemara understands that a חצר, chatzer,
the גמרא's Gemara idea of a חצר chatzer is a street with
a house. So if it adds the words בתים batim to the
word חצרים, chatzerim, it means that each street has two houses. Okay.
אי הכי לכתוב רחמנא חצרים, in kein lichtov rachmana chatzerim, וכי תימא
אי כתב רחמנא חצרים, ve'chi teima ee katav rachmana chatzerim, חצר
בלא בית משמע, chatzer belo bayis mashma,
maybe I would have thought that it means even without a house?
No, ההוא קרפף איקרי, hahu karpaf ikri, that's called a yard. But
a חצר chatzer is like a street and it means with a
house, and therefore the extra word בתים batim means two houses and
two streets, and even then it's not big enough. Now, the interesting
thing is, if you remember, the משנה Mishna says what do you
need to be considered a walled city? It says three streets with
two houses, because that goes beyond this definition. What if you had
two streets with three houses each? You know what I'm say? It's
interesting that the גמרא Gemara understands that the next move up, let's
say you had two houses with 10... two streets with 10 houses
each? Okay, so it's interesting, you know, where exactly you draw the
line, and the גמרא Gemara. says the next page is three streets.
Yes.
So I sell my house
when there's only two courtyards in this whole city, and then some
developer comes and builds a third courtyard.
That's after ימות יהושע בן נון, yemos Yehoshua bin Nun, doesn't matter.
It's only if it was that way from the time of יהושע
בן נון. Yehoshua bin Nun. Or from the time of עזרא, depending
on if you go first or second.
Has to stay that way? What?
No, the גמרא Gemara, says, אף על פי שאין לו עכשיו, af
al pi she'ein lo achshav, even though it doesn't have now,
as long as it had beforehand. It all goes by the way
it was at the time of either יהושע Yehoshua or עזרא.
It's very much like...
exactly what?
Exactly. What?
This
is why it's fun on פורים.
Purim. Right, exactly.
At random places that are... Right, exactly. ישראל שירש אבי אמו
לוי.
Yisrael she'yarash
avi imo Levi.
Now we're getting to לוי. Levi. Remember we said that לויים, Leviyim,
the פסוק pasuk said and we spelled out a minute ago, can
be redeemed, you know, always redeemed, whether house or field, always redeemed.
Now let's say you're not a לוי, Levi, but you inherit from
a לוי. Levi. So you inherited from your maternal grandfather a לוי,
Levi, but you're not a
לוי. Levi. Okay. אינו גואל כסדר הזה. eino go'el keseder hazeh. You
do not redeem like the previous law, like the ישראל Yisrael presumably
you have the rights of a לוי Levi because you're getting a
לוי's Levi land. וכן לוי שירש אבי אמו ישראל. ve'chen Levi she'yarash
avi imo Yisrael. How about the reverse? You're a לוי Levi that
inherited a ישראל's Yisrael land. You inherited your maternal grandfather's ישראל's Yisrael
land. So you're a לוי Levi with a
non-לוי Levi land. אינו גואל כסדר הזה. eino go'el keseder hazeh. You
do not redeem like the previous but presumably either way you have
the rights of a לוי. Levi. Now the גמרא is going to
re-read this as you'll see because it's got to contradict itself this
משנה. Mishna. שנאמר כי בתי ערי הלוים היא אחזתם shene'emar ki batei
arei haLeviyim hi achuzatam because the house of the cities of the
Levites is their inheritance. עד שיהא לוי בערי הלוים. ad she'yehai Levi
be'arei haLeviyim. It has to be you have to be both a
לוי Levi and it has to be a לוי's Levi land to
have these rights. So one minute. A second ago you just said
that even if I wasn't... even if only one of those. So
the גמרא is going to re-read the first half of the משנה
Mishna that instead of saying אינו גואל כסדר הזה eino go'el keseder
hazeh means אינו גואל אלא כסדר הזה. eino go'el ela keseder hazeh.
That if you are, because the משנה Mishna is clearly contradicting itself.
So if you just inherited from a לוי Levi or you just
are a לוי, Levi, you still have the law like a ישראל.
Yisrael. That's how it's going to read the first half of the
משנה. Mishna. What you need to have the special rights of a
לוי Levi is עד שהוא לוי וערי הלוים. ad she'hu Levi ve'arei
haLeviyim. דברי רבי. Divrei Rabbi. That's what רבי Rabbi says. וחכמים אומרים
אין דברים הללו אמורים אלא בערי הלוים. vachachamim omrim ein devarim halalu
amurim ela be'arei haLeviyim. And the Sages say, no, it doesn't matter
who you are, it matters that it is the field of the
לויים. Leviyim. The fields of the לויים Leviyim have a גאולה. geulah.
גאולת עולם geulat olam even if you inherited from your maternal grandfather
and you are not a לוי Levi yourself.
So גמרא says like this. So it starts by the beginning of
the משנה Mishnah which sounds like as long as you have one
of those, it's good enough. So if you have one of those,
you're not like the previous case. ואלא כמאן, ve'ella k'man, so then
who are you like if you're not like the ישראל? Yisrael? כבן
לוי, k'ben Levi, presumably even if you only have one of those
criteria, you're like a לוי. Levi. והדר תני, vehadar tani, and then
it says, עד שיהא לוי וערי לויים. ad she'yehei Levi ve'arei Levi'im.
You need to have both criteria, both a לוי Levi and the
city of the לויים. Levi'im. אמא, eima, so what you have to
do is you have to read the beginning of the משנה, Mishnah,
אינו גואל אלא כסדר הזה, eino goel ella k'seder hazeh, that if
you have only one of those criteria, you are stuck in the
first category of a ישראל, Yisrael, עד שיהא לוי וערי
לויים, ad she'yehei Levi ve'arei Levi'im, until you have both criteria, דברי
רבי. divrei Rebbi. Okay. So רבי Rebbi says you need both, and
the חכמים Chachamim say it only has to be what type of
land it is. בשלמא ערי לויים, bishlama arei Levi'im, I understand why
it's the land of the לויים, Levi'im, דכתיב, dechtiv, כי בתי ערי
הלוים, ki vatei arei ha'Levi'im, the houses of the cities of לויים,
Levi'im, that is their inheritance, and there should always be a גאולה,
geulah, emphasizes the city. אלא לוי
מנלן, ella Levi minalan, how do I know that you yourself have
to be a לוי? Levi? דכתיב, ואשר יגאל מן
הלוים, va'asher yigal min ha'Levi'im, because it says at one stage in
describing the rights of the לוי, Levi, it doesn't say if somebody
redeems the land of the לויים, Levi'im, it says if somebody redeems
from the לויים. Levi'im. So both describes the people and the land,
and you need both criteria. תניא, tanya, ואשר יגאל מן הלוים, va'asher
yigal min ha'Levi'im,
if somebody redeems from the לויים. Levi'im. יכול לוי מישראל יגאל, yachol
Levi mi'Yisrael yiga'el, maybe now it's asking a different question. When a
לוי Levi has rights to redeem at all times, maybe his rights
to redeem at all times is if he sold it to ישראל
Yisrael who's in a weaker category than he is. שזה יפה כחו
וזה הורע כחו, shezeh yafeh kocho vezeh hura kocho, לוי Levi has
more rights than a
ישראל, Yisrael, more power. אבל לוי מלוי לא, aval Levi mi'Levi lo,
maybe I would say if a לוי Levi sold to a לוי,
Levi, look, what's the reason that you're giving me rights? Because I'm
a לוי. Levi. But the other guy who bought it is a
לוי. Levi. So maybe he should be entitled to keep it. Maybe
I shouldn't be able to force him to give it back to
me. Maybe I would say שזה יפה כחו וזה יפה כחו, shezeh
yafeh kocho vezeh yafeh kocho, we both have the same rights. תלמוד
לומר, הלוים, talmud lomar ha'Levi'im, מן הלוים ולא כל הלוים. min ha'Levi'im
velo kol ha'Levi'im. Okay, so
some form of מן הלוים. min ha'Levi'im. So the דרשה derashah. is
מן הלוים min ha'Levi'im that somehow again, I'm not exactly sure how
it's getting
it, but the דרשה derashah, somehow let's see if the side sent
it.
הלוים. ha'Levi'im, No, no, it's not the מ. mem. ואשר... so the
מ is going to be in a minute. תלמוד לומר הלוים, ha'Levi'im.
from all times, all cases of לויים, Levi'im, anybody they redeem,
anybody that purchases from them they have a right to force back,
even from another לוי. Levi. Again, I'm not exactly sure the דרשה,
but the point is an important point, which is that you might
have thought that their right is to keep it as לוי Levi
field, so if they sell it to לוי Levi they don't have
a right, so somehow it's being learned out from the פסוק pasuk
that even if they sell it to a לוי, Levi, they have
a right to buy it back at all times. Now, now we're
going to do the other דרשה. מן הלוים, min ha'Levi'im, which is
the more obvious דרשה, from the לויים, Levi'im, ולא כל הלוים, velo
kol ha'Levi'im, not all the לויים Levi'im have this right. So they
have the right regardless of who they sell it to, but not
all לויים Levi'im have the right. Which לויים Levi'im don't have the
right? פרט לבן לוי ממזר ונתין. prat l'ben Levi mamzer u'netin. If
he is not a legitimate son. Now that's interesting because even if
he's a ממזר, mamzer, בנדון דידן, benidon didan, a לוי Levi that's
a ממזר mamzer is still a לוי, Levi, right, he can't marry
halakhically, but he still has the status of a לוי. Levi. But
somehow if it, which is interesting, because normally other than the prohibition
of marrying, right, there's not so often that we have exclusions relating
to ממזר. mamzer. Maybe sometimes in a בית דין considerations, anyway, there's
an interesting question about how much that status is translated in ways
outside of just his prohibition to marry. So here it's saying that
somehow מן הלוים, min ha'Levi'im, assuming like רבי Rebbi that it's not
enough that it's the field of לוי, Levi, you have to be
a לוי Levi in order to be able to have this special
privilege, if you're somehow not a legitimate child, you're a ממזר, mamzer,
ונתין, v'netin, which is a category similar which I'm not going to
get into, that is also excluded. Let's just finish and we'll take
a question. וחכמים אומרים אין דברים הללו אמורים אלא בערי לויים אף
על פי שאינו לוי. vachachamim omrim ein devarim halalu amurim ella be'arei
Levi'im af al pi she'eino Levi. No,
the person doesn't matter, all that matters is the field. So within
רבי Rebbi that the person matters, we see here חידוש chiddush beyond
just being a לוי, Levi, it's even not being, it's even being
a legitimate son as it were and not being a ממזר. mamzer.
Yes, Charles?
So a לוי Levi who's a ממזר mamzer would get the second
עליה and would be able to receive מעשר ראשון? ma'aser rishon?
I'm not ending by the way, we have five minutes left. Go
ahead.
So yeah, a לוי Levi who's a ממזר mamzer would be able
to receive מעשר ראשון? ma'aser rishon? Yeah. Wow.
Yeah. All right, now let's continue. משנה. Mishnah. אין עושים שדה מגרש.
ein osim sadeh migrash. Now that we're talking about לויים Levi'im field,
so the תורה Torah describes that the לויים Levi'im it says that
they have a thousand אמות amot outside their city, and it also
speaks about them having fields and מגרש. migrash. מגרש Migrash is and
fields are where you plant wheat. מגרש Migrash is understood to be
more like yards. And the way the גמרא the משנה Mishnah understands
it is that outside the cities of לויים Levi'im there would be
a thousand אמה amah radius which would just be like open fields
that weren't used for planting, like yards and greenery and whatever, and
then beyond those another thousand אמה amah radius that would be fields
that would be used for planting. And now the משנה Mishnah is
telling us that that structure of the city of לוי Levi has
to remain that
way. or the yard area into, the yard is not the right
word but whatever, into into like planting fields. ולא מגרש עיר, vlo
migrash ir, you cannot turn the yard area, you can't expand your
city and build out into the מגרש. migrash. ולא עיר מגרש, vlo
ir migrash, or you can't shrink your city and turn some of
the city into this yard area. אמר רבי אלעזר בן מנחם, Amar
Rabbi Elazar bin Menachem, אמורים בערי הלוים. amurim b'arei HaLevi'im. That's by
the cities of לויים Levi'im where the תורה Torah very clearly describes
how they're supposed to look. אבל בערי ישראל, Aval b'arei Yisrael, if
you just happen to have a Jewish city, you know it's all
flexible. There's no blueprints. עושים שדה מגרש, Osim sadeh migrash, you can
make your field into a מגרש. migrash. Now there's a question if
you have the word ולא here. Let's read it, let's take it
out, because that seems to be better the way the גמרא understands
it. או מגרש שדה, o migrash sadeh, so you can turn your
field into a yard, your yard into a field. מגרש עיר, Migrash
ir, you can turn your, you can expand your city and build
out into the yard area. But the one thing you can't do
even in a non-לוי Levi city is ולא עיר מגרש. vlo ir
migrash. You cannot turn a part of the city, you cannot now
demolish that and turn it into a yard. Why? שלא יחריבו את
ערי ישראל, Shelo yachrivu et arei Yisrael, not to destroy cities. Of
course there's a problem. I mean, the only reason you'd want to
do that is because the whole city is being abandoned anyway, right?
So you know, so is it really better to leave these houses
standing and uninhabited than to try to, it's an interesting question because
you won't do it capriciously. Yes, מגרש. migrash. מגרש Migrash like I
said is a, as opposed to a שדה sadeh which is like
where you're planting wheat, a מגרש migrash is sort of like unplanted
forest, it's grass, it's
the word probably has more to do with like is it מגרש
migrash what? Like לגרש? l'garesh? Oh, I don't know. It's a good
question what the root is. Yeah, I'm not sure. But it's basically
not abandoned. It's actually understood to be like aesthetic, meaning like you
have parks, right, parks,
forested, I think park was the better word than field than yard,
twice. So basically exactly like parks and forests and all that stuff,
and then that's right outside the city. You don't want to be
planting wheat right up to the city gate, and then as you
get further out, that's where you have your wheat fields. Parks is
the right metaphor, or not metaphor, model.
Yes. Okay, let's just finish it. הכהנים והלוים מוכרים לעולם וגואלים לעולם.
Hakohanim vehalevi'im mocherim l'olam u'goalim l'olam.
Interesting, although we've assumed this in the previous משנה Mishnah about the
whole status of לויים, Levi'im, here we're saying it. A לוי Levi
and a כהן Kohen can redeem it at all times, right? They
don't have to wait a year, they can redeem all the way
up to the יובל. They have the power to redeem at all
times and sell at all times as obvious, שנאמר גאולת עולם תהיה
ללוים, shene'emar geulat olam tihyeh lalevi'im, they can always redeem. Let's just
read a few lines in the גמרא.
In the city into into the מגרש. migrash. They can keep extending
the city.
No, לויים Levi'im cannot. ישראל Yisrael can. Yeah, ישראל Yisrael can. Sure,
you can keep on extending. Right. Okay, let's just read to the
two dots, get a little into the גמרא, go up to the
first wide line. אמר רבי אלעזר בן מנחם אמורים בערי הלוים אבל
בערי ישראל עושים את זה Amar Rabbi Elazar bin Menachem amurim b'arei
HaLevi'im aval b'arei Yisrael osim et zeh etcetera. So okay, it quotes
רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar in the משנה. Mishnah. דכולי עלמא מיהא בערי
הלוים לא משנינן. D'chulei alma miha b'arei HaLevi'im lo meshaninan. So רבי
אלעזר Rabbi Elazar pointed out that it's different with cities of non-לוי
Levi cities. But everybody agrees לוי Levi cities have to remain that
structure. Why? מנא הני מילי? Mena hanei milei? אמר רבי אלעזר דאמר
קרא ושדה מגרש עריהם לא ימכר. Amar Rabbi Elazar d'amar kra u'sadeh
migrash areihem lo yimacher. The fields of their מגרש, migrash, so we
have the mentioned fields and this מגרש, migrash, the park area, shall
not be sold. מאי לא ימכר? Mai lo yimacher? What does it
mean don't sell? אילימא לא ימכר כלל, Ileima lo yimacher klal, literally
don't sell? הא כתיב גאולת עולם תהיה ללוים, Ha ktiv geulat olam
tihyeh lalevi'im, it says you can redeem it at all times. Presumably
if you can redeem it means you could sell, שבכלל דמזדבני, shebechlal
d'mizdabnei, you could sell it. אלא מאי לא ימכר? Ela mai lo
yimacher? So לא ימכר lo yimacher does not mean don't sell, it
means לא ישנה. lo yeshaneh. You cannot change the structure. The parks
have to remain parks, the fields fields. You're allowed to sell it,
but then you can, but then you're entitled to buy it back,
but don't change the basic structure of what the city is supposed
to look like. And we will wrap up this מסכת. masechet.